Guide to the Rose Levy Beranbaum Papers MSS.285
Fales Library and Special Collections
Rose Levy Beranbaum Papers
1977-2011
2006-2009
Fales Library and Special Collections
Beranbaum, Rose Levy
MSS.285
6 Linear Feet in 4 record cartons, 1 legal-size manuscript box, one shared media box, and 3 oversize flat boxes.
14 Cassettes
1 sound disc (cd)
Rose Levy Beranbaum is a cookbook author, baker, and graduate of New York University's Steinhardt School of Culture, Education, and Human Development. This collection consists of manuscript drafts, galleys, and proofs, dated 2006-2009, for her cookbook, Rose's Heavenly Cakes (2010). It also contains cooking ephemera, conference proceedings, and cooking, nutrition, and food publications related to her research and work, dated from the 1970s to 2011.
Biographical / Historical
Rose Levy Beranbaum is a cookbook author, baker, and graduate of New York University's Steinhardt School of Culture, Education, and Human Development. She has published ten books and won three James Beard Awards: for her first book The Cake Bible in both Baking and Desserts, and Book of the Year, 1989; and for Rose's Christmas Cookies, Baking and Desserts, 1991.
She ran a cooking school out of her New York City apartment for ten years and has more than 150 videos on YouTube. She was a consultant for Proctor and Gamble and taped 13 episodes of "Baking Magic with Rose Levy Beranbaum", which began in 2004 on PBS and ran for three years.
Beranbaum has contributed to several national publications, including Food Arts Magazine, where "Rose's Sugar Bible" received the Association of Food Journalists Award for the Best Food Feature in a Magazine, and The Jacob's Creek World Food Award for Best Food Article.
She currently is an instructor for Craftsy through her online baking classes and maintains a blog, www.realbakingwithrose.com, launched in 2005.
Arrangement
Book manuscript versions are arranged sequentially, retaining the creator's original order according to version names and numbers. Cooking ephemera, conference proceedings, publications, and audiocassettes follow the manuscripts.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Rose Levy Beranbaum. Accession numbers associated with this donation are 2010.285, 2011.285, 2012.285, 2013.285.
Scope and Contents
The Rose Levy Beranbaum Papers consist of manuscript drafts, galleys, and proofs, dated 2006-2009, for Beranbaum's cookbook, Rose's Heavenly Cakes (2010). The collection also contains some cooking ephemera, conference proceedings, cooking and nutrition reports, pamphlets, and flyers related to Beranbaum's research and work from 1986 to 2011, plus 14 audio recordings on various cooking techniques from the 1970s.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact The Fales Library & Special Collections (fales.library@nyu.edu) with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Baking.; Cookbooks.; Publishers and publishing; Galley proofs.; Cooks.
- Version 1, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
- Version 2, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 3-4)
- Version 3, 2007 (Box 1, Folder 5-7)
- Version 4: semifinal ms, submitted on disk, undated (Box 1, Folder 8-11)
- Version 5, undated (Box 1, Folder 12-13, Box 2, Folder 1)
- Version 6: version 4, reformatted with font change, undated (Box 2, Folder 2-3)
- Version 7: Pam's editing, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Version 8: final ms. before copyediting, 2009 (Box 2, Folder 5-10)
- "Misc.", undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Version before page proofs with design, 2009 (Box 2, Folder 12-16)
- Version 9: copyedited, undated (Box 3, Folder 1-5)
- Global changes for Ava, undated (Box 3, Folder 6-10)
- Version 10: galleys 2, bound, 2009 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Version 11: galleys 3, 2009 (Box 3, Folder 12-14)
- Version 12: first pass, has photos, 2009 (Box 4, Folder 1-4)
- Version 13, 2009 (Box 6, Folder 1-5)
- First pass, master, 2009 (Box 6, Folder 6-8)
- First pass, master, with all corrections, 2009 (Box 7, Folder 1-3)
- Second pass, master, 2009 (Box 7, Folder 4-6)
- Third pass, master, 2009 (Box 8, Folder 1-3)
- Final corrections, 2009 (Box 8, Folder 4)
- Version 14: final pass from designer, 2009 (Box 8, Folder 5-6)
- Version 15: proofreader notes/corrections, production posting, notes to production editor, photography planning, 2008-2009 (Box 4, Folder 5-8)
- Global nutrition and food safety publications, conference proceedings, ephemera, brochures, 1987-2011 (Box 4, Folder 9-23)
- Biotechnology publications and reports, 1987-2006 (Box 5, Folder 1-5)
- USDA Food safety toolkit and CD, 2006 (Box 5, Folder 6, Box Shared Fales 006)
- Helen Feingold styling tips from Ruth Levy Beranbaum, circa 1970s (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Helen Feingold styling tips audiocassettes, circa 1970s; 14 Cassettes (Box Shared Fales 006, Cassette 1-14)